<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-06-10T19:04:25+00:00</updated><id>https://nkatikaneni.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">SaaS Security Posture Management - From Baseline Configurations to Penetration Testing</title><link href="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2025/sidebar-table-of-contents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SaaS Security Posture Management - From Baseline Configurations to Penetration Testing" /><published>2025-06-10T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2025/sidebar-table-of-contents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2025/sidebar-table-of-contents/"><![CDATA[<p>Enterprises today heavily rely on Software-as-a-Service (SaaS) for critical business functions, from email to collaboration tools, to CRM, to source code hosting. This dependence emphasizes the urgent need for robust Security Posture Management (SPM). Breaches exploiting SaaS misconfigurations underline the importance of clearly understanding the shared responsibility model where SaaS providers secure underlying infrastructure, but customers manage data protection, access controls, and compliance.</p>

<h2 id="shared-responsibility-in-saas-security">Shared Responsibility in SaaS Security</h2>

<p>Under SaaS models, vendors such as Microsoft or Google ensure infrastructure security and availability, while customers handle internal security configurations and data protection. Most SaaS vendors provide configuration guidance to customers on handling their data security, but more often this guidance tend to be confusing and/or is not customized to customer’s need. This leads to vulnerabilities out of misconfigurations. In fact, Gartner estimates over 99% of cloud breaches through 2025 will result from customer-side misconfigurations, highlighting a crucial area for enterprises to address.</p>

<p>Recent breaches underline this risk:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Salesforce Communities exposed sensitive data through overly permissive guest user settings.</li>
  <li>Misconfigured Microsoft 365 file-sharing settings caused significant data leaks.</li>
  <li>Google Workspace incidents demonstrated vulnerabilities due to unenforced security basics like MFA and third-party app controls.</li>
</ul>

<p>Understanding and managing customer-side responsibilities prevent costly breaches, regulatory penalties, and reputational damage.</p>

<h2 id="defining-secure-configuration-baselines">Defining Secure Configuration Baselines</h2>

<p data-toc-text="baseline-configurations">Secure configuration baselines outline essential security settings for SaaS applications, typically including but not limited to: MFA enforcement, role-based access controls, strong password policies, restricted external sharing, and proper data encryption. US Govt agencies receive extensive guidance and tools from organizations like Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency (CISA), National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) etc. Commercial enterprises can borrow similar concepts as federal agencies and can also refer to industry benchmarks (e.g., CIS Benchmarks for platforms like Microsoft 365, Google Workspace, Slack, and Salesforce) to define these baselines.</p>

<p>Typical security baseline areas:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Account Security:</strong> Mandatory MFA, SSO, removal of legacy authentication.</li>
  <li><strong>Access &amp; Privileges:</strong> Enforce role-based access controls and regular privilege reviews.</li>
  <li><strong>Data Sharing Controls:</strong> Restrict external data sharing and manage guest or anonymous access rigorously.</li>
  <li><strong>Monitoring &amp; Alerting:</strong> Enable built-in suspicious activity alerts and comprehensive audit logging.</li>
  <li><strong>Compliance Alignment:</strong> Activate settings compliant with HIPAA, GDPR, or sector-specific regulations.</li>
</ul>

<p>Managing SaaS baselines involves continuous automated checks against security best practices and compliance frameworks. Enterprises leverage scripts, APIs, or SaaS Security Posture Management (SSPM) tools for ongoing audits and remediation of configuration drift.</p>

<h2 id="emerging-sspm-solutions">Emerging SSPM Solutions</h2>

<p data-toc-text="sspm">The proliferation of SaaS necessitates automated solutions to oversee security effectively, leading to the emergence of SaaS Security Posture Management (SSPM) platforms. SSPM tools act as centralized hubs, continuously monitoring SaaS configurations and integrations via agentless API connections. These platforms offer:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Unified visibility into SaaS security.</li>
  <li>Automated detection of configuration drift.</li>
  <li>Compliance management aligned with standards like SOC 2, HIPAA, or ISO 27001.</li>
  <li>Threat detection capabilities through behavior analytics.</li>
  <li>Easy orchestration for remediation.</li>
</ul>

<p>Leading SSPM platforms include Obsidian Security, Adaptive Shield, AppOmni, DoControl, Wiz SSPM, and Microsoft Defender for Cloud Apps, each specializing in different aspects of SaaS configuration and security management.</p>

<h2 id="saas-specific-threats-and-vectors">SaaS-Specific Threats and Vectors</h2>

<p data-toc-text="saas-security">Securing SaaS applications requires vigilance against unique threats:</p>

<ul>
  <li>OAuth Token Abuse: Attackers exploit OAuth consents (consent phishing), bypassing MFA to gain persistent access.</li>
  <li>Over-Provisioned Access: Excessive privileges and dormant accounts pose significant risks, emphasizing regular privilege audits.</li>
  <li>Session Hijacking: Attackers target session tokens via malware, requiring conditional access and session controls.</li>
  <li>Integration Abuse: Malicious third-party apps connected to core SaaS platforms can enable data exfiltration.</li>
  <li>Phishing via Collaboration Tools: Attackers leverage trust in collaboration apps like Slack or Teams to distribute malicious payloads.</li>
  <li>Insider Threats: SaaS applications facilitate easy data sharing, increasing risks of data leakage and insider threats.</li>
  <li>Hybrid Attack Paths: Attackers blend SaaS breaches with attacks on internal infrastructure, exploiting interconnected identities and data flows.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="saas-penetration-testing--continuous-monitoring">SaaS Penetration Testing &amp; Continuous Monitoring</h2>

<p>Penetration testing of SaaS focuses primarily on customer-specific configurations, user privileges, and integrations, respecting provider constraints. Typical test areas include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Configuration audits to identify permission issues.</li>
  <li>Credential and phishing attack simulations.</li>
  <li>Evaluating third-party integrations for data exfiltration potential.</li>
  <li>Tenant isolation verification and custom scripting vulnerabilities.</li>
</ul>

<p>Continuous monitoring via SIEM integration or dedicated SSPM tools is crucial. SaaS providers’ native logs (e.g., Unified Audit Log in Microsoft 365, Google Workspace logs) combined with centralized monitoring provide comprehensive threat detection. Effective monitoring includes establishing alerts for suspicious activity, privilege changes, abnormal data transfers, and OAuth token abuses.</p>

<h2 id="enterprise-use-cases-and-scenarios">Enterprise Use Cases and Scenarios</h2>

<p>Concrete enterprise examples demonstrate SPM in action:</p>

<h3 id="financial-institutions-microsoft-365--salesforce">Financial Institutions (Microsoft 365 &amp; Salesforce)</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Prioritize customer data security and compliance.</li>
  <li>Implement strict conditional access, encryption, and comprehensive privilege reviews.</li>
  <li>Leverage SSPM tools for ongoing compliance monitoring.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="tech-companies-slack-github-google-workspace">Tech Companies (Slack, GitHub, Google Workspace)</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Focus on intellectual property protection.</li>
  <li>Enforce strict access controls, MFA, and context-aware access.</li>
  <li>Integrate DevSecOps practices and comprehensive DLP policies.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="healthcare-organizations-zoom-workday">Healthcare Organizations (Zoom, Workday)</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Emphasize compliance with HIPAA and data privacy.</li>
  <li>Implement stringent telehealth security features and extensive audit logging.</li>
  <li>Conduct regular phishing and incident response drills to validate protective measures.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="best-practices-and-summary">Best Practices and Summary</h2>

<p>A robust SaaS Security Posture Management strategy combines technology, defined processes, and cross-team collaboration:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Inventory &amp; Baseline:</strong> Catalog SaaS applications and establish detailed, compliant security baselines.</li>
  <li><strong>Automate Audits:</strong> Utilize SSPM tools or automated scripts to ensure continuous monitoring against defined baselines.</li>
  <li><strong>Centralized Monitoring:</strong> Integrate SaaS logs into SIEM solutions for comprehensive visibility and proactive threat detection.</li>
  <li><strong>Regular Training &amp; Exercises:</strong> Equip teams with updated SaaS security training, regular phishing simulations, and red-team exercises.</li>
  <li><strong>Cross-functional Collaboration:</strong> Encourage cooperation among IT, security, compliance, and SaaS application owners to reinforce security posture.</li>
  <li><strong>Lifecycle Management:</strong> Incorporate security reviews at each phase of SaaS adoption and ensure thorough user offboarding.</li>
  <li><strong>CISA/NIST Guidance:</strong> Incorporate extensive research and tooling provided by dedicated security researchers at CISA, NIST and associated organizations. While their guidance has a federal agency focus, most concepts are equally applicable to commercial organizations.</li>
</ul>

<p>In conclusion, SaaS Security Posture Management is an essential practice for enterprises leveraging cloud solutions. Through clear definition, continuous vigilance, and collaborative efforts, organizations can significantly reduce their SaaS security risks, ensuring data protection, regulatory compliance, and operational resilience.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="baseline-configurations" /><category term="sspm" /><category term="saas-security" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a blog post on SaaS security posture management for enterprises]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with custom blockquotes</title><link href="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2023/custom-blockquotes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with custom blockquotes" /><published>2023-05-12T19:53:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-12T19:53:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2023/custom-blockquotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2023/custom-blockquotes/"><![CDATA[<p>This post shows how to add custom styles for blockquotes. Based on <a href="https://github.com/sighingnow/jekyll-gitbook">jekyll-gitbook</a> implementation.</p>

<p>We decided to support the same custom blockquotes as in <a href="https://sighingnow.github.io/jekyll-gitbook/jekyll/2022-06-30-tips_warnings_dangers.html">jekyll-gitbook</a>, which are also found in a lot of other sites’ styles. The styles definitions can be found on the <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/blob/master/_sass/_base.scss">_base.scss</a> file, more specifically:</p>

<div class="language-scss highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cm">/* Tips, warnings, and dangers */</span>
<span class="nc">.post</span> <span class="nc">.post-content</span> <span class="nt">blockquote</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">&amp;</span><span class="nc">.block-tip</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">border-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nl">background-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block-bg</span><span class="p">);</span>

    <span class="nt">p</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block-text</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="nt">h1</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h2</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h3</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h4</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h5</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h6</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block-title</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="k">&amp;</span><span class="nc">.block-warning</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">border-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nl">background-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block-bg</span><span class="p">);</span>

    <span class="nt">p</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block-text</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="nt">h1</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h2</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h3</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h4</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h5</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h6</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block-title</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="k">&amp;</span><span class="nc">.block-danger</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">border-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nl">background-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block-bg</span><span class="p">);</span>

    <span class="nt">p</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block-text</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="nt">h1</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h2</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h3</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h4</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h5</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h6</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block-title</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A regular blockquote can be used as following:</p>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; This is a regular blockquote</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; and it can be used as usual</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is a regular blockquote
and it can be used as usual</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These custom styles can be used by adding the specific class to the blockquote, as follows:</p>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; ##### TIP</span>
<span class="gt">&gt;</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; A tip can be used when you want to give advice</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; related to a certain content.</span>
{: .block-tip }
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote class="block-tip">
  <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5>

  <p>A tip can be used when you want to give advice
related to a certain content.</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; ##### WARNING</span>
<span class="gt">&gt;</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; This is a warning, and thus should</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; be used when you want to warn the user</span>
{: .block-warning }
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote class="block-warning">
  <h5 id="warning">WARNING</h5>

  <p>This is a warning, and thus should
be used when you want to warn the user</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; ##### DANGER</span>
<span class="gt">&gt;</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; This is a danger zone, and thus should</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; be used carefully</span>
{: .block-danger }
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote class="block-danger">
  <h5 id="danger">DANGER</h5>

  <p>This is a danger zone, and thus should
be used carefully</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><category term="blockquotes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with custom blockquotes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog" /><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nkatikaneni.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>